Register of the N. N. Baratov papers
Hoover Institution Archives
N. N. Baratov papers
1898-1965
81131
Hoover Institution Archives
4 manuscript boxes, 3 envelopes (1.8 linear feet)
Correspondence, memoranda, diaries, reports, military documents, maps, clippings, and printed matter relating to Russian military activities in Persia and the Caucasus during World War I, and to the Russian Revolution. Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Baratov, N. N.
Access
Collection is open for research. Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1981.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Alternate Forms Available
Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Biographical Note
1865 February 1 Born, Ardon, Sunezhskaia Stanitsa, Caucasus
1874-1891 Graduated from Second Konstantinovskoe Military Academy, Nikolaevskoe Engineering School, Academy of the General Staff
1891-1906 Military service in the Caucasus
1915 Decorated with the Order of St. George
1916-1918 Commander of the Russian Expeditionary Force in Persia with rank of general
1918-1920 Took part in Civil War with Volunteer Army of South Russia; immigrated to France after defeat of White forces
1921?-1932 President of the Federation General des Invalides Mutiles de Guerre Russes a l'Etranger
1932 March 22 Died, Paris, France
Scope and Content of Collection
Correspondence, memoranda, diaries, reports, military documents, maps, clippings, and printed matter relating to Russian military activities in Persia and the Caucasus during World War I, and to the Russian Revolution.
Russia. Armii͡a--Officers.; World War, 1914-1918--Campaigns--Iran.; World War, 1914-1918--Russia.; Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921.
- BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIAL, 1901-1932 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Official documents and excerpts from printed material dealing with the military career of General N. N. (Nikolai Nikolaevich) Baratov. Arranged chronologically.
  - Official documents and printed matter, 1901-1932 (Box-folder 1: 1)
- DIARIES, 1898-1931 (Boxes 1-2)
  Handwritten journals by Baratov, arranged chronologically.
  - 1898 (Box-folder 1: 2)
  - 1914 (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - 1916 (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - 1918-1919 (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - "My Trip to India,", 1918 September-October (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - "India,", 1918 December - 1919 January (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - 1920 (Box-folder 2: 2)
  - 1922 (Box-folder 2: 3)
  - 1922 (Box-folder 2: 4)
  - 1925 (Box-folder 2: 5)
  - 1929-1931 (Box-folder 2: 6)
  - "Memoirs of H.R.H., Prince A.P. Ol'denburgskii Recorded During My Stay at His Country House in Machelon, Biarritz,", undated (Box-folder 2: 7)
  - Album, undated (Box-folder 2: 8)
- RUSSIAN EXPEDITIONARY FORCE IN PERSIA, WORLD WAR I FILE, 1916-1965 (Box 3)
  Official correspondence with General Head Quarters (G.H.Q.), elements of the expeditionary force, and the Russian Embassy in Tehran; miscellaneous correspondence and documents re Russian Expeditionary Force in Persia (R.E.F.P.); Baratov's farewell address to the troops; and newspaper clippings and printed material re R.E.F.P. in contemporary and émigré press. Arranged by physical form.
  - Correspondence
    - General, 1916 August 15 - 1917 January (Box-folder 3: 1)
      Official copies of correspondence between Baratov, G.H.Q., the Russian Embassy in Tehran, and elements of his expeditionary force re military and political situation on the Persian Front.
    - Finance, 1917 September 29 - 1919 March 12 (Box-folder 3: 2)
      Official correspondence re financial situation and supply of R.E.F.P.
    - Miscellaneous, 1916 May 5 - 1918 (Box-folder 3: 3)
      Correspondence and documents re R.E.F.P.
    - Withdrawal from Persia, 1917 December 9 - 1918 February (Box-folder 3: 4)
  - Farewell address of General Baratov to the troops of the R.E.F.P., 1918 June 10 (Box-folder 3: 5)
  - Printed matter
    - Newspaper clippings and printed matter re R.E.F.P.
      - Contemporary press (Box-folder 3: 6)
      - Émigré press (Box-folder 3: 7)
    - Printed material and handwritten notes of P. N. Baratov, 1965 (Box-folder 3: 8)
  - Writings
    - Inostrantsev, M., "L'operation de Sarykamych," Revue Militaire Francaise, No. 164-165, Paris, 1935 February-March (Box-folder 3: 9)
    - Kromiadi, K., memoirs re R.E.F.P., 1917-1918 (Box-folder 3: 10)
    - Anonymous, essay re political situation and foreign policy of Persia after the Russian Revolution (Box-folder 3: 11)
- CIVIL WAR FILE, 1917-1920 (Box 4)
  Miscellaneous documents re Civil War, Volunteer Army of South Russia and revolutionary movement in the Kuban'-Terek Region and the Caucasus. Arranged by physical form.
  - Documents, revolutionary movement in South Russia and the Caucasus, 1917-1918 (Box-folder 4: 1)
  - Miscellaneous, documents and correspondence
    - 1919 July-December (Box-folder 4: 2)
    - 1920 January-February (Box-folder 4: 3)
  - Report by "E.I.V." re Civil War in the Terek-Kuban' Region and the Caucasus, 1918-1920 (Box-folder 4: 4)
- EMIGRATION FILE, 1921-1965 (Box 4)
  Personal and family correspondence of Baratov and his wife, Vera N. Baratov; printed material and correspondence of the Federation General des Invalides Mutiles de Guerre Russes a l'Etranger; miscellaneous documents of Russian émigré organizations; and clippings from Russian émigré and French press. Arranged by topic.
  - Clippings, Russian émigré and French press, 1931-1932 (Box-folder 4: 5)
  - Correspondence
    - Personal, 1921-1927 (Box-folder 4: 6)
    - Vera N. Baratov, 1935-1943 (Box-folder 4: 7)
  - Federation General des Invalides Mutiles de Guerre Russes a l'Etranger
    - General correspondence, 1921?-1929 (Box-folder 4: 8)
    - Brochures and printed material, 1928-1965 (Box-folder 4: 9)
    - Newspaper clippings (Box-folder 4: 10)
  - Miscellaneous documents, Russian émigré organizations, 1921?-1928 (Box-folder 4: 11)
- PHOTOGRAPHS, circa 1914-1918
  - 36 prints depicting Russian Expeditionary Force in Persia, including groups of Kuban, Orenburg and Eiisk Cossacks, 1916-1918; 53 prints of Persia, including landscape, people and monuments, as well as some prints of meetings between the command of the Russian Expeditionary Force and local authorities (Envelope A)
  - 9 prints, including Nicholas II, Emperor of Russia and his son; portraits of General N. N. Baratov, 1914-1918 (Envelope B, m*C)